Finding Aid for Shien-Ming Wu Papers 1960-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Shien-Ming Wu papers
1960-1992
1975-1987
Wu, Shien-Ming, 1924-1992
9802 Aa 2
Professor of mathematical engineering at the University of Wisconsin, 1962-1987, and University of Michigan,1987-1992, developed the "the dynamic data system approach" to manufacturing, served as consultant to Ford, General Motors, Chrysler and other manufacturers. Papers document his teaching, research and consulting activities.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Daisy T. Wu, wife of Shien-Ming Wu, (Donor 8661 ) in 1997.
The collection is open for research.
Shien-Ming Wu was a professor of mechanical engineering at the University of Wisconsin and the University of Michigan. Shien-Ming Wu, or "Sam" as he was known to his friends and colleagues, was born in Chekiang, China in 1924. Wu graduated from Chiao-Tung University, Shanghai in 1945. Nine years later he came to the United States and earned his master's degree from the Wharton School. Wu then went to the University of Wisconsin where he obtained his doctorate in mechanical engineering in 1962. Following graduation he became a professor of mechanical engineering at the University of Wisconsin and held that position for nearly 30 years. In 1987 he retired at Wisconsin and came to teach and to do research at the University of Michigan. In 1975 he was named a Fulbright professor and traveled to the former Yugoslavia to teach. In 1988, he was again named a Fulbright professor and traveled to the former Soviet Union to teach. In December 1991, Wu became the first recipient of an $100,000 award from the Chiang Industrial Charity Foundation in Hong Kong. The award is given to an "ethnic Chinese"" who has created a unique, new manufacturing technology or invention. Wu donated his prize money to the University of Michigan, to create an endowment for manufacturing engineering students. During his long career he trained 113 doctoral students and wrote over 300 articles for scientific and engineering journals. In addition to Wu's academic career he also developed "the dynamic data system approach." This new way of manufacturing was used to modernize Ford, General Motors and Chrysler as well as other companies around the world. In all, he did consulting work for over thirty major companies. Shien-Ming Wu died on October 28, 1992.
The collection is divided into four series:
Correspondence, 1963-1989
Topical Files, 1964-1992
Reprints, 1963-1986
Teaching/Research Materials, 1963-1987.
The Dr. Shien-Ming Wu papers, 1960-1992, document his activities as university professor of mechanical engineering, research scientist and consultant on a variety of industrial projects. The papers include considerable Chinese language materials.
Subjects:
Wu, Shien-Minh, 1924-1992.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering.; Mechanical engineering.; Chinese Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Correspondence, 1963-1992
  Correspondence, the first series, is composed of the subseries "Alphabetical" and "Chronological." The letters in "Alphabetical" are from students who did their graduate work with Wu. Researchers should be aware that several of the letters in this series are in Chinese. The "Chronological" subseries of letters focuses on the projects that Wu worked on for major corporations.
  - Alphabetical, 1963-1989
    - A-N, 19 folders (Box 1)
  - Chronological, 1966-1992; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters of congratulations, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
- Topical Files, 1964-1992
  The second series, Topical Files, contains much information about the projects and companies that Wu worked with during his career. The wide variety of industries that he was involved with will be of interest to the researcher. The majority of this series consists of correspondence, reports and proposals. The final two folders of this series are entirely in Chinese and it is not known what type of information they contain.
  - Advanced Technology Program, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Auto Body Consortium Papers, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME) Blackall Machine Tool and Gage Award, 1981-1986 (Box 2)
  - Automotive Papers
    - circa 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Automotive Proposals, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Biographical Information (Box 2)
  - Bob King's Drill, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Chen, Simon, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Clippings/Press Releases (Box 2)
  - DeVor Tool and Die, 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Douglas Aircraft, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Drill Grinders
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1985 (Box 2)
  - Dynamic Data Process Quality Control, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Electric Power Research Institute
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
  - Electric Power Research Institute Proposal, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Ford, Process Illustrations, Grant, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Funding Summary, 1985 (Box 2)
  - General Dynamics
    - Report, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Tube wrapping machine, 1978-1981 (Box 2)
  - General Electric- Burlington, Vt., 1979-1983 (Box 2)
  - General Motors, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - General Motors Projects, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Industrial Technology Institute, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Lockheed Georgia, Co., 1982 (Box 2)
  - Mechanical Industry Research Laboratories, Report, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Mechanical Technology, Inc., 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Metal Industries Development Center, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Mini-Review Committee of the Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Mobil Teaching Unit, 1966 (Box 2)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1989 (Box 2)
  - National Center for Mechanical Sciences, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation, 1965 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation Proposals
    - 1984 (Box 3)
    - 1986, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Project PDS, 1-5 (Box 3)
  - Projects/Proposals, 1988-1992 (Box 3)
  - Proposals for Fellows (Box 3)
  - Publishing/Royalties, 1981-1983 (Box 3)
  - Quality Control, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Research Projects
    - 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - 1985, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Rock Island Arsenal, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - S-Grinders, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Saginaw Machine Systems, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Teaching Proposal, 1987 (Box 3)
  - TSAO, Tsu-Chin, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Tube Identification, 1981 (Box 3)
  - U of M Corporate Relations, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Yen, James, 1981-1983 (Box 3)
  - Chinese Language Material, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Reprints, 1963-1986
  The series Reprints contains many articles by Wu that were published in scientific and engineering journals. He has hand dated all of these in the order that they were published.
  - Scholarly Articles, 8 folders (Box 3)
- Teaching/ Research Materials, 1963-1987
  The series Teaching/Research Material, consists of the documents that Wu used to instruct many of the mechanical engineering students he taught at the University of Wisconsin and at the University of Michigan. Dr. Wu's research material and draft material for the many papers which he wrote are also included in this series.
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers Papers, 1964-1981 (Box 4)
  - Engineering Statistics (Box 4)
  - Lecture Notes for Experimental Course, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Mechanical Engineering Teaching Materials
    - Course no.123, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Course no.322, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Course no.324, 1965 (Box 4)
    - Course no.346, A report on the course, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Course no.347, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Course no.516-05 (Box 4)
    - Course no.560, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Course no.903, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Papers on Dynamics and Control, 1967-1981 (Box 4)
  - Research Papers
    - Pau-Lo Hsu, Y.B. Chen and S. Wu (Box 5)
    - H.S. Kim, K.F. Eman and S. Wu, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Jianjun Shi, Jun Ni and S. Wu (Box 5)
    - Yixin Yao and S. Wu, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Response Surface Method, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Single Sampling Plan (Box 5)
  - Statistical Experimental Design for Engineers, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Statistical Methods for Quality Control, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Statistical Quality Control, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Teaching Materials, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Time Series and Systems Analysis- Modeling and Applications, 1979 (Box 5)